<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the French kinge his good successe, in winning from the Duke of Parma, his fortes and trenches, and slaieng 500. of his men, with the great famine that is now in the sayd dukes campe With other intelligences giuen by other letters since the second of May. 1592. A most wonderfull and rare example, the like wherof, neuer happended since the beginning of the world, of a certaine mountaine in the Ile of Palme, which burned continually, for fiue or six weeks together, with other both fearful &amp; stra[n]ge sightes, seene in the ayre, ouer the same place.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03006</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851872</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17165</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03006)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1309:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the French kinge his good successe, in winning from the Duke of Parma, his fortes and trenches, and slaieng 500. of his men, with the great famine that is now in the sayd dukes campe With other intelligences giuen by other letters since the second of May. 1592. A most wonderfull and rare example, the like wherof, neuer happended since the beginning of the world, of a certaine mountaine in the Ile of Palme, which burned continually, for fiue or six weeks together, with other both fearful &amp; stra[n]ge sightes, seene in the ayre, ouer the same place.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Wolfe, and are to be sold at his shop, ouer against the South-dore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes separate title page (register and pagination are continuous) that reads: A most vvonderfull and rare example, the like whereof, neuer happened since the beginning of the world.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alessandro Farnese, --  Duke of Parma, 1545-1592.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Las Palmas (Canary Islands) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:1"/>
                  <p>A TRVE RELATION of the French Kinge his good <hi>ſucceſse, in winning from the Duke of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> his Fortes and Trenches, and ſlaieng 500. of his men, with the great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine that is now in the ſayd Dukes Campe. With other intelligences giuen by other Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſince the ſecond of May. 1592. A moſt wonderfull and rare example, the like wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, neuer happened ſince the beginning of the world, of a certaine mountaine in the Ile of Palme, which burned continually, for fiue or ſix weeks together, with other both fearful &amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſightes, ſeene in the ayre, ouer the ſame place.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of John Wolfe, featuring a fleur-de-lis seeding (McKerrow 216)</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſold at his ſhop, ouer againſt the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore of Paules. 1592.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:2"/>
                  <head>A true Relation of the Frenche <hi>Kinge his good ſucceſse, in winning from</hi> the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> his forts and trenches, and ſlaieng 500. of his men, and the great famine that is now in the ſayd Dukes Campe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt true it is which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> in the 13. to the <hi>Romans</hi> auoucheth of Kinges and Princes, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng there is no power but of God, and the powers that bee are ordained by God. And no leſſe true is that Golden ſayeng of the princelie Prophet Dauid, ſpeking in the perſon of God: by me kinges rule, and by me doo princes exerciſe authoritie.</p>
                  <p>Then it followeth neceſſarilie, that as kings and princes vppon earth are the ordinance of God, (and therefore thoſe that do reſiſt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt them doo reſiſt the power of God, and purchaſe to themſelues eternall damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17165:3"/> as the ſame Apoſtle beareth record: ſo the Lord will, and dailie dooth (as wee ſee by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience euery daye) bleſſe the ſame his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, confounding, ſcattering, and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the practiſes, or rather the trecherous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiraces of all thoſe that riſe vp againſt his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.</p>
                  <p>Which thing the Lord hath moſte notablie perfourmed euen the laſt day vpon the French King, that valiant ſouldiar of his, giuing vnto him moſt happie and fortunate ſucceſſe againſt the Duke of <hi>Parma.</hi> VVho albeit he be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a man of puiſſance and valor, yet the Lord our God (bleſſed be his holie name therfore) to manifeſt to the worlde, how muche his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in aiding the rebellious Leaguers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Soueraigne Kinge and liege Lord, dooth diſpleaſe him, he croſſeth him in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and as it were ſtandeth before him, and fighteth againſt him, ſometimes ſtriking a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine terror and feare into his heart, with the reſt of his complices, and other-ſometimes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowing them altogither in their owne plats and deuiſes, according to the ſayeng of the Pſalmiſt, The wicked hath digged a pitte for others, but is fallen into it himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But to come to the matter, as it pleaſed god it fell out thus.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> hauing now the ſecond or third time inuaded the kingdom of France
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17165:3"/> with a puiſſant and mightie Armie, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to aide the rebellious Leaguers, agaynſte their lawfull Kinge, paſſing the confines, and entring (as it were) into the bowelles of the Realme, approched with his armie neere vnto the Cyttie <hi>Roane,</hi> who beeing purſued by the King and his people, drew himſelfe farther off towardes <hi>Newhauen,</hi> and there hee incamped himſelfe, raiſing moſt ſtrong Fortes, and erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (as hee thought) trenches inuincible for his owne and his ſouldiers better defence: yea ſo ſtronglie had he intrenched himſelfe there, planting ordinance, Baricadoes, and other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie munition of infinite varietie, that hee thought himſelfe not onelye able to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile what ſtrength the king ſhould be able to bende againſt him, but alſo he ſuppoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be in effect inexpugnable.</p>
                  <p>But as the prophet <hi>Eſaias</hi> ſaith, there is no wiſedome, there is no pollycie, there is no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, nor ſtrength againſt the Lord, nor againſt his annointed.</p>
                  <p>For the King by ſecret intelligences or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, beeing aduertiſed of the Duke his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and how ſtronglie he had fortified him ſelfe in Trenches and bulwarks, with all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpeed marched towardes him, taking with him ſuch a competent number of horſſemen, and footmen, as he thought ſufficient to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the forces of the aduerſarie.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17165:4"/>
                  <p>Being come ſomewhat neere the place, he cauſed his armie to march forwarde both lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurelie and aduiſedlie, the better to preuent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ambuſhes: and viewing with prouidente eie the manner of his enimies lyeng, their Fortes, their trenches, and other their muny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, at the laſt with mature aduiſe, and moſt peremptorie reſolution (as one that fighteth the Lords battels) in moſt fierce manner aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his enimies on euerie ſide.</p>
                  <p>And albeit the fight was both long and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, and ſeemed a great while to hang in equall ballance, neither inclining vnto the one nor to the other, yet it pleaſed God, who continually fighteth for his ſeruantes, that the Kinge pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled.</p>
                  <p>And although he had not in his band ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie as the Enimie was by oddes, yet he wanne the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> his Fortes and Trenches, mauger the heads of all his enimies, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his men to flie back and to retire to a more narrower place, beeing conſtrained to fortifie themſelues anew, in ſuch place as they coulde get on the ſuddaine, and it is verilye thought that they can not be able to holde out longe againſt the forces of the King.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> alſo (ſuch was the migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie hand of God againſt him) not onelye loſte his fortes and trenches, but 500. of his chiefeſt ſouldiers alſo, beſides other munition &amp; great
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17165:4"/> ſpoiles.</p>
                  <p>The Duke is nowe preſentlie ſo driuen to the wall, and ſo corbed vp, al hope of new ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of viandes or victuals, being in ſome ſorte intercepted and cut off from him, that he with his whole armie are ſo ſore aſſailed with famin, as that they are forced to eate their horſſes for verie hunger.</p>
                  <p>Thus haſte thou heard Gentle Reader the noble exploits of that valiant King of France, with his good ſucceſſe (which God continue:) and the preſent ſtate of the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> with his retinue, whoſe hande the Lorde of Hoſtes ſhorten, and ſtrengthen that illuſtrious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noumed French King, that he may fighte the Lords Battels ſtill, that once (if it be his bleſſed will) poperie, ſuperſtition and Idolatrie maye bee cleane rooted out, and true religion maie vniuerſally be planted in all Chriſtian Kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17165:5"/>
                  <head>By letters receiued on the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of May.</hi> 1592.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N Thurſday laſt beyng the ſeuen and twentith day of Aprill, 1592. The Duke of Parma did go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by night to <hi>Cleere,</hi> which is within foure leagues of <hi>Roane,</hi> without anie drumme or trumpet ſounding, and on the next daie being Friday, the king followed him with a number of hys horſemen, to moue him to the battaile. The Duke left behind him his artillerie, and his baggage.</p>
                  <p>On the Saterday before, the king had taken the Dukes Trenches, and one Fort which hee had made, and at the ſame time there was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eight hundred of the Dukes menne ſlaine.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of Sauoy, hath bene forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire out of Prouence.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17165:5"/>
                  <p>The cittie of <hi>Aix,</hi> which held for the ſaid Duke of Sauoie, who maried the king of Spain his daughter is reuolted from him, and nowe preſentlie houldeth for the king.</p>
                  <p>The Muſcouites haue giuen a great ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw to the Tartarians.</p>
                  <p>There is in Germanie ſome rumor of ciuill wars amongeſt themſelues.</p>
                  <p>Cicilia and Italie doo feare an other great dearth this next yeare.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17165:6"/>
                  <head>Newes out of the Low Countries.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Countie Mauritz</hi> hauing aſſembled a great power is nowe before <hi>Steinwiche</hi> in <hi>Frizeland,</hi> with fiftye good peeces of ordinance and dooth beſiege it fierce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie, with purpoſe to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſame if by anie poſſible meanes it may be perfourmed. The Lord grant ſuch ſucceſſe as may ſtand with his glorie, and the good of his church, Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:6"/>
                  <p>A MOST VVONDER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and rare example, the like <hi>whereof, neuer happened ſince the</hi> beginning of the world. OF A CERTAINE <hi>MOVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in the Ile of Palme, which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> continually, for fiue or ſixe weeks together. With other both fearefull, and ſtrange ſights, ſeene in the ayre, ouer the ſame place.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of John Wolfe, featuring a lion, tiger or dragon's head facing outward (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:7"/>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17165:7"/>
                  <head>TO THE COVRTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader: Grace <hi>and peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, thou haſt heere before thine eyes a moſt rare example, and no leſſe ſtrange inſtance, of the vvonderfull vvorks of God, the trueth vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſuch, as is auouched by diuers, both honorable and vvorſhipfull, and others of good credite. VVherfore read it vvith iudgement, make thy profite of it, and giue God the glorie, vvho be bleſſed and praiſed for euer.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:8"/>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17165:8"/>
                  <head>A moſt vvonderful and rare <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the like whereof neuer happened ſince</hi> the beginning of the world, of a certain moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, <hi>in the Ile of Palme, which burned continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> for fiue or ſixe weekes together, with other both fearefull and ſtraunge ſightes, ſeen in the ayre, ouer the ſame place.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Goſpel of S. Mathew, the 24. Chapter, our ſauiour Chriſt telleth vs of many ſignes and tokens, which ſhal be ſent vnto vs and appeare before the day of iudgment, as that the ſonne ſhalbe darkened, the Moone ſhall looſe hir light, the Starres ſhall fall from heauen, the earth ſhall tremble, and ſhake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs, the hilles ſhalbe ſupplanted and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of their places: the Seas ſhall roare and make a hideous noyſe, there ſhall be wars and rumours of warres in all countries, and ſuch like. All which ſignes and tokens we ſee to be come to paſſe alreadie. For if wee take
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17165:9"/> the ſonne in that place, for the ſonne of God Chriſt Ieſus (as all ſound expoſitions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretors haue done:) howe often haue wee ſeene him darkened, and obſcured with the filthy miſtes, and ſtincking vapors of mens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. The Moone that is the Churche of God, how was ſhee darkened, yea almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of her light vnder the tyrannie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt the pope of Rome and his ſhauelings? The Starres, that is the paſtors, and miniſters of the Church, how were they driuen away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Papiſtes, from the firmament of ſounde doctrine, and pure conuerſation. But if we take theſe ſignes literally, howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times haue we ſeene the ſunne and moone to be eclipſed, and almoſt manie times to loſe their whole light. What woonderfull and ſtrange coniunctions of Starres of ſignes and plannets, threatning euen an vniuerſall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of all things haue we ſeene of late yeares. The like was neuer ſeen of many yeares before. What firie meteers, blaſing Starres, Comets, and other fearefull impreſſions haue we ſeene in the ayre of late yeers? What inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and ouerflowings of the ſeas and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? What fearefull earthquakes? What remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of hilles out of their places? What Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, fearefull and monſtrous birthes? What warres and rumours of warres in all countries, doe we heare of in theſe daies? All which are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17165:9"/> infallible tokens, and apparant arguments that the day of iudgement is at hand, and as it were before the dores. But although the Lord our God hath and doth dayly as well by theſe ſignes and tokens aboue named, and the like, as alſo by others of infinite varietie, ſummon vs to the doome, and warneth vs to be alwaies readie and prepared, yet hath hee not in anie age, nor to anie people, ſent a more fearefull, ſtrange, or woonderfull example (as it were a warning or caueat to all the world) then this that followeth, the trueth whereof was thus.</p>
                  <p>There is a certaine Iland called <hi>Palme</hi> nere to the <hi>Ingenio</hi> of <hi>Tertia</hi> court, three leagues from the Citie, and a league and a halfe from the ſea ſide, wherein grewe a certaine moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or hil of three hundred faddam in height, and a league and a halfe in compaſſe. This mountaine or hill, the 19. of May beganne to burne, and ſo continued ſtill burning till the 19. of Iulie next after, in moſt ſtrange and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full maner.</p>
                  <p>Vpon the top of which hill there ſeemed to be a great caue or gulfe: whereat iſſued out great flames of fire; burning in ſuche forcible and vehement maner, as they raiſed vp withall and caſt foorth huge and mightie ſtones into the ayre, ſtinging them vp with great violence, which ſtones at the length deſcending downe againe foorth of the ayre, fell downe at the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17165:10"/> foote of the ſame hill. And yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it continually burned in this ſort, and caſt forth infinite great and monſtrous ſtones, yet the ſaid hill remained ſtill in all mens iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as bigge as it was before. The heate of which fire was ſuch, and ſo great that the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereabouts were ſore annoyed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, hauing their vineyards and their corn ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and burnt vp thorow the rage and vyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the flames of fire that iſſued thereout. And in this ſorte it continued vntill the 20. of Iulie about midnight at which time the ſayd mount or hill, brake in ſunder, and ſhiuered in peeces, cauſed ſuch great cracks and roringes, as though it had thundered, or a hundred can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons had beene ſhot off, to the great terror of the hearers.</p>
                  <p>It beeing thus diſſeuered and broken, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued burning: And burning (contrarye to the nature thereof before) conſumed and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, till it came to be as it were a great coale of fire, from which cole there ſeemed to aſcende and to riſe vppe into the aire as it were great mountaines of ſmoke and ſparkles of fire, as bigge in appearance as little barrels, and ſo at the laſte the whole mountaine conſumed and burned away.</p>
                  <p>There guſhed alſo foorth of the ſayd moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine (before it was conſumed) great ſtreames of water, burning like oile in the fire, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17165:10"/> vp woonderfull flames into the aire, which entred into the Sea fourty faddame, makinge all the water thereabout ſo extreame hot, as it melted the pitch and roſine wherewith the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers botes were pitched.</p>
                  <p>The heat of this burning water was ſuch, as it ſcalded and killed all the fiſhe neere therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, ſo that aboundance of fiſhe of all ſortes was found dead many dayes after.</p>
                  <p>From this mountaine alſo there tumbled downe to the Sea-ſide, beeing diſtante from thence a league and a halfe three mighty great ſtones, one of them being 25. faddom in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, and with a woonderfull violence threw themſelues into the Sea fiftie faddame at the leaſt.</p>
                  <p>The hill being in this ſort quite conſumed, the ſecond of Auguſt next following there rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned downe foorth of the aire, as it had beene whole ſhewers of blacke aſhes, like gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in bigneſſe, which ſpoiled and conſumed all the Corne, graſſe, and vines in the whole countrey about.</p>
                  <p>After this, namelie the fourth of Auguſt, it rained againe great ſtore of white aſhes in the Cittie, the ſtreets being ſo thicke couered ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with as the people coulde not trauaile about their neceſſarie buſineſſe. Immediatlie after this: to wit, the fourth of September folowing, there appeared ouer the ſame Iland in the aire,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17165:11"/> other ſtrange and wonderfull ſights, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly armed men to the number (as a man would haue thought) of 40000, one fighting againſte another in moſt cruell &amp; bloudie maner, with ſuch fearefull thundering, and terrible lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as the like was neuer heard nor ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The people ſeeing theſe ſtrange ſightes, and feareful wonders, called to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: repented of their ſinnes, and inſtantlye beſought the Lord that he would not enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement with them, nor puniſh them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſertes: whiche done, the Lord in mercy withdrew his plagues, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes, (meſſengers of his wrath) from them, and receiued them to mercie. Thus haſt thou heard courteous Reader, the true narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wonderfull iudgementes of God againſt this people. The Lord giue both them and vs all grace, to make profite of them, and to amend our liues, that we may altogether in the great day of the Lord receiue the crown of euerlaſting glorie, promiſed vnto vs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17165:11"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, this note comming to my hands before the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hereof vvas ended, <hi>I</hi> thought it good to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part it vnto thee, rather out of place, then not at all, as a thing vvhich vvill giue thee great light to the great vnderſtanding of the vvhole book.</p>
                  <p>This Ile of <hi>Palme</hi> ſpoken of before, is one of the ſeuen Ilandes of the <hi>Canaris,</hi> vvell knovvne to diuerſe merchantes here in London. <hi>Ingenio</hi> is ſcituate vvithin the ſame Iland.</p>
                  <p>Manie of the inhabitantes vvhereof <hi>I</hi> meane of the <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Palme,</hi> vvere forced to go out, and to depart from thence, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking their landes, goodes and all, and to dvvell ſome of them at Gomorra, ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17165:12"/> of them in the <hi>Ile</hi> of Tenerife, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the graund <hi>Canaris,</hi> ſuppoſing verily that the ſame Iland vvoulde haue ſunke. And for the great aboundance of aſhes, vvhich rained dovvne, they coulde not ſovv their corne in October follovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>The lieuetenant of the Iland, ſent the narration heereof to the court of Spaine being at <hi>Madrill,</hi> penned by a notarie publick, vvith three other notaries hands to it, deſiring certaine Lordes of the ſame Court, to ſend their opinion, vvhat theſe fearefull tokens might prognoſticate.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17165:12"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
